Guide to the Sir Isaac Newton Collection, 1684-1949
Department of Special Collections
Sir Isaac Newton Collection,
1684-1949
Special Collections M0132
2.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
The major part of this collection consists of the donations of Frederick E. Brasch who was Chief of the Scientific Collection of the Library of Congress before coming to Stanford where he served as a consultant in bibliography from 1948 to 1967. Several items were purchased from dealers including: William H. Schab of New York, Dawsons of Pall Mall, Ifan Kyrle Fletcher of London, and W. Heffer and Sons Ltd of Cambridge, England. More recent additions include xerox copies of Newton material from the Newton Exhibition in Nottingham, donated by A. Noel Proctor in 1966. Newton manuscript fragment [on church history, etc.], gift of Haskell Norman 1974.
Scope and Content
The Newton Collection manuscripts consist of letters, drafts, reports, notes, bound volumes of lecture notes, tables, diagrams, portraits, printed pamphlets and booklets, and photostats by and about some of the leading figures in the history of science. It includes material by or about George Biddell Airy, Jean Baptiste Biot, David Brewster, Albert Einstein, Johann Franz Encke, John Flamsteed, William Rowan Hamilton, George William Hill, Nevil Maskelyne, Albert A. Michelsen, Isaac Newton, Nicholas Saunderson, and John Winthrop. Time span is ca. 1684-1949.
The collection is particularly strong in the areas of astronomy, physics and mathematics. The Isaac Newton material includes notes on his invention of calculus, geometric notes and diagrams, and some manuscripts concerning alchemy, and in addition, xerox copies of letters and manuscripts relating to his duties as warden of the Royal Mint. There are also bound volumes of lecture notes of Nicholas Saunderson's mathemetics lectures at Cambridge University. The Einstein material includes some early printed booklets in German and some letters dating from both his early years in Germany and his later residence in the United States. The material on astronomy includes several bound volumes of notes on celestial mechanics by Geroge William Hill and William D. Morgan.
The materials are arranged alphabetically by author, although several subgroups include materials written by other individuals which concern a particular scientist. Thus, grouped under Albert Einstein are letters by Brasch and others relating to Einstein's life and work. Each subgroup is organized according to the different types of material it contains, i.e. letters, manuscripts, bound volumes, etc. Material is organized chronologically where dates are available and by titles where they are not.
Container List
- Abbe, Cleveland, 1838-1916: (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To Prof. Benj. Persie (with U.S. Coast Survey), Jan. 4, 1869., ALS, 2pp.
  - Loan of self-recording apparatus [added May 1968].
- Adams, John Couch, 1819-1892: (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - To Fisher, July 3, n.y., ANS, 1 p
- Airy, Sir George Biddel, 1801-1892: (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - To Fred L. Rogers, Feb. 13, 1837., ALS, 1 p
  - To John Barlow, May 30, 1857., ALS, 3 pp
  - To Walter White, Dec. 22, 1863., ALS, 1 p
  - To R. S. Newall, July 24, 1871., ALS, 1 p
- Alexander, Sir James Edward, 1803-1885: (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - To John Russell Bartlett, Nov. 18, 1841., ALS, 2 pp
- Anseted, David Thomas, 1814-1880: (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - To Dr. Davis, n.d., ALS, 2 pp
- Bache, A.D., 1806-1867: (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - To S.P. Chase, Sec. of Treasury, May 2, 1861., ALS, 2 pp
  - Autograph of A.D. Bache, [added May 1968]., 2 pp, 2 copies
- Bell, [] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - To Mr. Hutton, Oct. 23, 1826., ANS, 2 pp
- Bernoulli, Familie: (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Geneological tables, holograph by unknown, including some equations. German or Swiss dialect, n.d., 11 pp
- Biot, Jean Baptiste, 1774-1862: (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - To M. Bayley, in French, Aug. 18, 1814., ALS 2 pp
- Bond, William Cranch, 1789-1862: (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - To Dr. Francis, Jan. 7, 1848., ALS, 2 pp
  - Report to the Committee on the Observatory, AD&S, May 15, 1846., 15 pp
- Bosworth, Joseph, 1781-1868: (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - From John S. Storr, July 18, 1866., ALS, 1 p
  - From John S. Storr, Oct. 16, 1866., ALS, 1 p
  - From George Stephens, Oct. 3, 1866., ALS, 4 pp
  - From George Stephens, Oct. 22, 1866., ALS, 4 pp
  - From Raymond Storr, Jan. 2], 1869., ALS, 1 p
  - From Raymond Storr, LS, Jan. 23, 1869., 2 pp
- Brewster, Sir David, 1781-1868: (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - To Marc I. Brunel, with seal, March 31, 1826., ALS 2 pp
  - To James Hudson, Sept. 13, 1832., ALS, 4 pp
  - To unknown, May 28, 1851., ALS, 2 pp
  - Portrait, signed lithograph, n.d., 1 p
- Crew, Henry, 1859-1953: (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - To Prof. Tyler, Oct. 1, 1930., ALS, 3 pp
- Dana, E.S., 1849-1935: (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - To Mr. Kung [?], June 30, 1888 [added May 1968]., ALS, 1 p
- Dartmouth, George Legge, 1st Baron, 1648-1691: (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - To Charles Bertie, July 26, 1684,ordering payment of allowances to several persons, including John Flamsteed (Flampsteed), with docket., ALS, 2 pp
- Einstein, Albert. Materials by or about Albert Einstein. Brasch, Frederick E., 1875-1967: (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - To Albert Einstein, TL, May 19, 1927., 1 p
  - To J. McKeen Cattell, TL, Feb. 14, 1929., 1 p
  - To J. McKeen Cattell, TL, Feb. 23, 1929., 1 p
  - To Josepha Whitney, TL, Apr. 23, 1929., 1 p
  - To Mrs. [Anita Newcomb] McGee, TL, May 16, 1930., 1 p
  - To Josepha Whitney, and AN, Nov. 28, 1941., TLS 1 p
- Einstein, Albert, 1879-1952: (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1. To [Josepha] Whitney, in German, July 15, 1926.Re: Simon Newcomb., ALS 2 pp
  - 2. [Verifax] copy of No. 1.
  - 3. Typed translation of No. 1 by Tobias Dantzig with ms. corrections, n.d., 2 pp
  - 4. Typed translation of No. 1 by Dantzig with ms. editing and TN by F.E. Brasch, n.d., 2 pp
  - 5. Autograph translation of No. 1 by Myrtis Jarrell, n.d., 5 pp
  - 6. Typed translation of No. 1 by Myrtis Jarrell, n.d., 3 pp
  - 7. Galley proof of Brasch's introduction and edition of the Dantzig translation of No. 1, Feb. 21, 1929., 1 p
  - 8. AMs of introduction to No. 7, n.d., 1 p
  - 9. TMs of introduction to No. 7 with carbon copy, n.d., 2 pp
  - 10. TMs of introduction to No. 7 with ms. corrections and carbon copy, n.d., 2 pp
  - 1. To The History of Science Society, TSL in German, June 4, 1927., 1 p (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 2. To F.E. Brasch, with cover, pledge, pamphlet, and return envelope, Jan. 20, 1947., TLS 8 pp
- Einstein Printed Material (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1. Eine Neue Bestimmung der Molek[UNK]uldimensionen, 1905.
  - 2. Sitzungsberichte der K[UNK]oniglich Preussischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 1914.
  - 3. Ather und Relativit[UNK]atstheorie, 1920.
  - 4. Die Kompatibilitat der Feldgleichungen in der Einheitlichen Feldtheorie, 1930.
- Hendrick, Burton J., 1870-1949: (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - To Mrs. Anita Newcomb McGee, with from Mrs. McGee To Brasch, Apr. 18, 1927., ANS TLS 1 p
- McGee, Anita Newcomb
  - To Mr. Brasch, with note by [Brasch], Mar. 29, 1930., ALS 3 pp
- Whitney, Josepha
  - To Mr. Brasch, Nov. 9, 1941, TLS, 1 p
  - To Mr. Brasch, n.d., ALS, 1 p
- Einstein Miscellany (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1. Clips announcing a lecture by Einstein at the University of Chicago, Apr. 29, 1921., 1 p
  - 2. Clip, obituary notice of Dr. Anita N. McGee, Oct. 8, 1940., 1 p
  - 3. To F.E. Brasch, Invitation to a lecture series by Professor Albert Einstein on the Theory of Relativity at Princeton, Apr. [?], 1921.
- Encke, Johann Franz, 179]-1865: (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - AMs and tables, July 12, 1824., 4 pp
- Flamsteed, John, 1646-1719: (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - To Henry [Normanthrop?], [Dec.] 31, 1696., ALS, 3 pp
  - Certificate of employment of Thomas Weston, signed C. Musgrave, Wm. Bridges, and Ja. Lowsher, ADS, Apr. 27, 1703., 1 p
  - Certificate of employment of Joseph Crussthwait, ADS, 1714., 1 p
- Halley, Edmond, 1656-1743: (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - To [Wallis], facsimile, Dec. 11, 1686., ALS 1 p
- Hamilton, William Rowan, 1805-1865: (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - To Charles Hatchet, Jan. 19, 1829., ALS, 2 p
  - To Capt. Beauford, (handwriting and signature differ from other two), Mar. 5, 1834., ALS 2 pp
  - To [Atkinson?], 2 00, Mar. 10, 1835., ALS
- Hill, George William, 1838-1914: (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Course of Lectures on Celestial Mechanics, bound holograph volume, prepared for delivery at Columbia College, 1893-1894.Edited by T. J. J. See, 1942-1943-1949. Hadnwritten editing also, except for a few printed insertions. Includes a letter, from J.L. Farnum to T. J. J. See, Apr. 29, 1915., TLS, (loose)
- Hockett, John (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - To Isaac Newton, with notes on chronology in Newton's hand in margin and on address sheet, Sept. 14, 1699., ALS 3 pp
- Leverrier's Tables, bound holograph volume, copied by H.C.F.C.Schjellerup, given to L.L.E. Dreyer, Aug. 1888. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811: (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - To Francis Wingrave, AL, Jan. 26, 1796., 2 pp
- Michelsen, Albert A., 1852-1931: (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - To Mr. H.W. Tyler (M.I.Y.), appoints Tyler member of of National Research Council, June 26, 1926., TLS, 2 pp
- Morgan, William D. (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Notes on Celestial Mechanics, bound holograph volumes with typed title page, introduction, and table of contents, 1950., 2 volumes
- Newton, Sir Isaac, 1642-1727: (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Alchemical writers, list of authors and books on alchemy including a list of 27 items headed: Desideratum opera Lulli sequentia, and some geometric notes, n.d., AMs, 11 pp.
  - Alchemical Writers, De Scriptoribus Chemicis, a bibliography containing titles and particulars of over 80 printed books and several mss., n.d., AMs, 5 pp (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lucatello's Balsalm, To make Lucatello's Balsome, a recipe. AMs and facsimile, n.d., 2 pp (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Philalethes, Notes out of Philalethes, beginning: Mercury vulgar is prepared for conjunction with sol vulgar by frequent cohabations of Reg of [Iron], n.d., AMs, 3 pp (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Philosophical and Theological Arguments concerning the Protestant and Catholic churches, n.d.,plus fragment. (Gift of Associates of the Stanford University Libraries), AMs, 16pp (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Raymundus, Ex Raymundi libro secretorum, sue de Quintessentis and notes (in Latin) on the separation of elements under Saturn and Jupiter, n.d., AMs, 13 pp (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Theatrum Astronomiae Terrestris, [and ye conversion of one element into another in ye composition of ye stone.] In English and Latin with two pen and ink diagrams. n.d., AMs, 4 pp; typescript with copies of diagrams, 5 pp (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Temple of Solomon, a sketch with holograph notes, facsimile, n.d.,from Schab catalog., 1 p
  - Notes [on church history, celibacy, and so forth], fragment, n.d.(Gift of Dr. Haskell Norman), AMs 2 pp (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notes [on motion in a circle], 1pp with typed copy in Latin with English translation, n.d.[added May 1968]., AMs, 8 pp, (9 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Notes [on planets], fragment, n.d., AMs 2 pp (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - To Halley, facsimile, Mar. 1, 1724/5., ALS, 1 p
  - Xerox copies of Newton items from the Newton exhibition in Nottingham. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence:
      - 1. To Mr. [Owen?]. Mar. 19, 1671., ALS, 11 p
        Re: telescope.
      - 2. To unknown, June 20, 1682., ALS, 1 p
        Re: theory of vision.
      - 3. To Mr. Bennett, Mayor of Chester, Apr. 16, 1698., ALS
        Re: one William Cook, a counterfeiter.
      - 4. To unknown, Nov. 23, 1699., ALS, 1 p
      - 5. To the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury, n.d., ALS, 1 p
    - Documents:
      - 6. Disposition of Newton's estate, A.D.S. (Henry Farrant, Deputy Registrar) with typescript copy, May 5, 1727., 2 pp
      - 7. An Account of the Mint in the Tower of London, n.d., AMs, 1 p
      - 8. An Account of the Scotch Money, n.d., AMs, 1 p
      - 9. Calculus, Newton's invention of, n.d., AMs, 1 p
      - 10. Concerning the Language of the Prophets, n.d., AMs, 1 p
      - 11. To make Lucatellos Balsome, n.d., AMs, 1 p
      - 12. Observations upon the state of the Coins of Gold and Silver, n.d., AMs, 1 p
      - 13. Proposals for coining half pence and farthing, of Copper for the English Plantations in American, n.d., AMs, 1 p
      - 14. Proposals for preserving and encouraging the coyn of this kingdom without hindering of freedom of Trade, n.d., AMs, 1 p
      - 15. Of an Universal Language, n.d., AMs, 1 p
      - 16. Untitled AMs n.d., 1 p
        Re: coinage duty.
      - 17. Unittled AMs with drawings of coins, n.d., 1 p
      - 18. Unidentified AN, n.d., 1 p
- Newton Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bound volume with many portraits, book plate, photos, clips, biographical sketch, facsimile ca. 1704-1858,includes:, ALS
    - To unknown, AL in Latin with typescript translation, June, 7th day of the kalends, 1704.
    - DS - two financial documents, May 4 and Dec. 24, 1718.
    - To Mr. MacLauren, and typescript, Aug. 21, 1725., ALS
    - Loose sheet with short holograph quotations from two of his scientific works, n.d.
- Polgar, Magyar and Teleki, Graf A. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - To unknown, in Hungarian, n.d.Re: a contribution to a math journal., ALS 4 pp
- Rogers, Henry, 1808-1866: (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - To Dr. Robson, n.d., ALS, 3 pp
- Saunderson, Nicholas, 1682-1739: (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - fragment, n.d., ANS, 1 p
  - Portrait etched, n.d., 1 p
- Notes by [W. Ludlam] from Saunderson's Mathematics Lectures, Bound, 1736. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Commentaries on several parts of Newton's Principia Philosophia by Professor Saunderson, lecture notes of W. Ludlam, bound, 1738. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- A Treatise of Fluxions by Nicholar Saunderson, copied by William Ward, bound, 1738-1739. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Clavis Newtoniana sive Commentarius in Principia Philosophia Newtoniana by Nicholar Saunderson, copied by W. Ludlam, bound, 1739. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- A Comment upon the Elements of Fluxions [by Nicholas Saunderson], copied by W. Ludlam, bound, 1739. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- The Elements of Fluxions by Nicholas Saunderson, copied by W. Ludlam, bound, 1739. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Logometria by N. Saunderson, copied by W. Ludlam, bound, 1739. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Simson, Rob [?] [Robert?] (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - To Mr. Colin Campbell, Feb. 14, 1718., typescript copy, 1 p
    [Probably transcribed by F.E. Brasch]
- Taggart, W.T. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - From H.W. Taeuber, Aug. 30, 1933., TLS, 1 p
- Van Vleck, J.M., 1833-: (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - To Prof. Tyler, Dec. 17, 1902. [added May 1968]., ALS, 4 pp
- Winthrop, John, 1714-1779: (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Summary of a Course of Experimental Philosophical Lectures, photostat from original at Harvard, n.d., AMs, 154 pp